むった
なんば
(南波六太)《ここに入って まだ
２０分ぐらいか…》
I've only been in here for twenty minutes.
I can't see a thing.
《何も見えない…何か
すんげぇ怖くなってきた…》
This is starting to get to me.
Stay calm...
ひびと
《落ち着け…日々人だって
これを耐えたんだ…》
Hibito managed to make it through this.
《チクショー ３次試験が➡
Damn, I didn't expect the third exam would be so intense!
ここまで過酷だなんて
思ってなかったな》
あ…！ん？ん？え…!?
Huh?
何の臭いだ…!?
What's this smell?
何か臭うぞ！何だ？何の臭いだ!?
I smell something...
What?
What's this smell?
何だ…何だ…何なんだ!?
What? What?
What...
この臭いは…！
is this smell?!
(ケンジ)≪ムッ君｡ムッ君！≫
Mu.
(ケンジ)着いたよ ムッ君｡
We've stopped, Mu.
Everyone's already gotten off the bus.
今 みんなバス降りてるよ｡
Oh...
＜というわけで 私達を乗せた
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡのバスは➡
And so, we arrived on the JAXA bus
どことも知れない 謎の３次試験
会場に到着したのである＞
at the third exam's undisclosed location.
Space Brothers
Ah
This feels so good, different from usual
I have no idea what's going on
It feels so good
I never understand what's going on around me
Nothing makes sense to me
Full of questions
Feel so moon
I danced with you in a desert lit by the moon
I won't lose to the rabbit and fly high
I'll fly high
#11 Trapped Rivals
どこだろうな ここ…｡
I wonder where we are...
(ケンジ)全く外が見えない…｡
We can't even look outside.
ぶ…不気味だ…｡
This is creepy.
ふるや
(古谷)なんや お前｡
ビビっとるんか？
What's this? You're scared?
つるみ
(鶴見)荷物はもう
中に運んであります｡➡
Your luggage has been taken inside.
皆さん ついて来て下さい｡
Please follow me.
Heh.
(せりか)は～｡天井 高～い｡
Wow, the ceiling's so high!
せま
狭っ…｡
It's so narrow.
And long...
《長いな…》
にった
《出発から何時間経ったのか➡
How many hours has it been since we left?
Is it night now?
全く分からなくなった…》
(古谷)《今は夜か…？それとも
１日経って もう朝か？》
Has a day already passed, meaning that it's morning?
この部屋です｡入って下さい｡
This is the room.
Please enter.
うおぉ…｡
Whoa.
どうぞ 椅子にかけて下さい｡
Please have a seat.
皆さん 長旅お疲れ様です｡➡
I'm sure that everyone is tired after the long trip.
ここは 我々ＪＡＸＡ職員が➡
JAXA calls this area the last room.
｢最後の部屋｣と
呼んでいる空間です｡➡
きつえん
喫煙や自由な飲食は
ともに ここが最後です｡➡
This will be your last chance to freely smoke, eat, or drink.
この先の閉鎖環境訓練施設に
持ち込みはできません｡
You cannot bring anything into the training facility's sealed environment.
そして もうひとつ…｡
And one more thing...
(鶴見)ここは 最後の選択の場でも
あります｡➡
This is where you will make your final decisions.
めんせきしょ
お配りの免責書に
よく目を通して下さい｡
Please read the disclaimer very carefully.
選択とは すなわち➡
You will have to decide whether you still want to take this exam.
今回この試験を
受けるか受けないか➡
キャンセルできる
最後のチャンスです｡
This will be your final chance to back out.
《へっ｡ここまで来て
受けへん言う奴おったら➡
Heh, if someone bailed at this point, I'd laugh.
爆笑モンやで！》
しょうだく
承諾のサインは
今から流す映像を➡
You can make your decisions after you've watched this clip.
見てから決めて下さい｡
NASA provided this video,
ナサ
(鶴見)これは ＮＡＳＡに
提供してもらったもので➡
to show to all candidates who reach the final exam.
最終選考まで残った者には
見せることになっています｡➡
一般公開は されていません｡
This footage has never been made public.
《この人は確か…》
I'm pretty sure that's...
(鶴見)皆さん 2023年の事故は
ご存じですね？➡
Is everyone here familiar with the 2023 accident?
着陸船のパラシュートが絡まり
ブライアン･ジェイら➡
The parachutes became tangled during landing,
resulting in the deaths of three astronauts, including Brian Jay.
３名の飛行士が
亡くなった事故です｡
これから お見せするのは➡
We will be showing you
footage of the spacecraft's interior, which was salvaged from the wreckage.
墜落現場から回収された
船内の録画です｡
事故死までの３人の
一部始終が映っています｡
This depicts the astronauts in the moments that led up to the crash.
そんな映像があったのか｡
There was footage?
R-Roger, I'll check the monitor...
[VTR](ﾏｲｹﾙ)りょ 了解｡
モニタで見てみる｡
Cut the alarm! We can't talk over that noise!
[VTR](ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)警報アラームを切れ！
会話の邪魔だ!!
[VTR](ﾀｯｸ)了解！
Roger.
I just checked the monitor!
[VTR](ﾏｲｹﾙ)
今 モニタで確認した｡➡
Damn it, the parachutes are tangled!
ちくしょう！パラシュートが
絡まってやがる!!ダメだ！➡
It isn't working...
The capsule's spinning out of control!
機体が回転して 全く安定しない｡
終わりだ ちくしょう!!
We're done for!
[VTR](ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)落ち着け マイケル！
できる事はやろう｡➡
Stay calm, Michael!
Just do what you can!
Tuck, keep Mission Control updated.
かんせい
タック！状況を管制に
報告してくれ｡➡
できるだけ細かく｡
俺とマイケルは 落下速度と➡
Send as much detail as you can.
Michael and I will calculate our current velocity and time remaining before impact.
地上までの時間を計算する｡
[VTR](ﾀｯｸ)りょ 了解！
R-Roger!
[VTR]今後の事故調査で
きっと役に立つ｡
The data from this accident will be very useful.
Twenty seconds until we hit the surface.
[VTR]地上まで あと２０秒だ｡➡
Damn, there was so much left I still wanted to do.
くそっ やり残したことが
いっぱいだな｡➡
買ったまま聴いてないＣＤとか➡
I never got to listen to the CD I just bought.
連続ドラマの
｢ラスト･ワールド｣だって➡
And I only watched up to episode 6, season 2, of Last World.
シーズン２の
６話目以降 まだ見てない｡
You chose a good place to stop, Michael.
[VTR]そいつは いいとこで
見終わったな マイケル｡➡
Huh?
After episode 6,
あのドラマ ６話目以降は…➡
超つまんないぜ｡
that show really sucked.
(鶴見)以上です｡
That is all.
くれぐれも これを見たことは
誰にも話さないで下さい｡➡
Please do not discuss what you just saw with anyone.
これを見せたのは
宇宙飛行士にとって➡
The purpose of this video is to serve as a reminder
事故に遭う可能性は
ゼロではないということを➡
that accidents can happen.
再確認してもらうためです｡
そして 彼らのように➡
And to determine if you're prepared to accept death, the way they did.
死を受け入れ
行動し続ける覚悟があるか｡➡
覚悟ができたという方は
書類にサインをして下さい｡
If you feel you are, please sign the disclaimer.
A few people are hesitating.
《すぐにペンを持たない者も
数名いる》
《当然だ｡その気持ちは分かる》
It makes sense...
I understand how they feel.
《自分には関係ないと思う者｡➡
There are those who think they'll never be in an accident.
There are the foolhardy who don't believe they can die.
自分が死ぬわけないと
強気な者｡また その逆…｡➡
And there's the opposite side.
死んだら死んだで
仕方がないと割り切る者｡➡
Some have decided their deaths are beyond their control.
色々いるだろう｡色々…》
Everyone has their own reasons,
different reasons.
《俺は…俺は死にたくはない！》
I...
I don't want to die!
《だけど…もう
やることは決まってる》
But I already decided to do this.
《死ぬのは嫌だが…➡
I don't want to die...
But I definitely don't want to die before I've made it to space!
死ぬまでに宇宙に行けない
ってのは もっと嫌だ！》
３０分ほど
ここで待ってもらいます｡
Please wait here for thirty minutes.
Anyone who's still undecided may use the full time.
悩んでいる人は
ギリギリまで悩んで下さい｡
てしま
おい 手島ぁ｡お前サインは？
Hey, Teshima...
Aren't you going to sign?
あ…これを飲んだら書くよ｡
I'll sign after I drink this.
どうやら 全員
承諾していただいたようですね｡➡
It appears that everyone has signed the waiver.
では 説明しますので➡
Before I explain the next part,
今から言うＡ Ｂ Ｃの
３班に分かれて下さい｡
we need you to divide into three teams.
３班？
Three teams?
(鶴見)まずはＡ班｡➡
First, we have Team A.
Ｂ班｡➡
Team B.
そして Ｃ班｡
And Team C.
この５人１組の
Ａ Ｂ Ｃの３班は➡
These three five-person teams
バスの中で皆さんに書いて頂いた
アンケートを元に構成しました｡➡
were assigned based on the surveys you completed on the bus.
我々から見て
あなた方１５名は➡
From our perspective,
all fifteen remaining candidates are very qualified.
全員 とても
優秀な人材と言えます｡➡
誰が選ばれても おかしくはないし
文句もありません｡
We would be glad to accept any of you as an astronaut.
これから Ａ Ｂ Ｃ ３班は➡
Next, Teams A, B, and C
それぞれ 別の閉鎖環境ボックスに
入ってもらいます｡
will each enter separate sealed environments.
そこで２週間…
与えられる様々な課題を➡
The five team members will spend the two weeks
working together to complete various tasks.
５人で協力し合い
こなしていって下さい｡
そして…最終日が来たら➡
And on the final day,
各班 互いに話し合いをして➡
each team will hold a discussion
全員 意見一致のもと
５人の中から２人だけ➡
and come to a consensus on the two members
宇宙飛行士に
ふさわしい者を選んで下さい｡
who would make the best astronauts.
最終日が来たら
各班 互いに話し合いをして➡
And on the final day,
each team will hold a discussion
and come to a consensus on the two members
全員 意見一致の元
５人の中から２人だけ➡
who would make the best astronauts.
宇宙飛行士に ふさわしい者を
選んで下さい｡
それから 最後にもう１つ｡
And I have one last thing to tell you.
《せりかさんと同じ班になれて
うちょうてん
一瞬 有頂天になったが➡
I was ecstatic about being on the same team as Serika,
とんでもないぞ｡自分達で選べって
そりゃないんじゃないの!?➡
but that was a mistake.
We're supposed to decide ourselves?
That isn't a good idea.
That makes us rivals,
それじゃ グループって言うより
敵同士じゃないか》
not teammates...
(新田)《このハゲが言った
最後の言葉が気になる》
I'm curious about that guy's final comment.
And I have one last thing to tell you.
⦅それから 最後にもう１つ｡➡
３チームで２人ずつ 計６名が
選ばれることになりますが➡
A total of six candidates,
two from each team, will be chosen.
But there may be additional candidates selected.
その他に ＪＡＸＡからも
かのうせい
数名選ぶ可能性があります⦆
(一同)⦅え!?⦆
⦅それは１人か２人か➡
There may ultimately be one, two, or even zero.
もしくはゼロか 未定ですが…⦆
It's not yet known.
《選ぶ人数が決まってないなんて
あんのか？》
They haven't decided how many astronauts they'll select?
《ありえへん｡何であの２人と
同じ班やねん！➡
I don't believe this!
Why am I on their team?
南波兄と新田…｡
バスで書いたアンケートで➡
Nanba's brother and Nitta...
Mizoguchi Yamato
Fukui Ryuunosuke
Nitta Reiji
Nanba Mutta
I put them at the bottom of my list!
ベベとブービーにした奴らやで｡➡
I don't like them because they're too tall.
でかいから
ムカツク２人｡かと思えば➡
But I ranked Fukuda pretty high, and he's also on this team.
割と上位に書いた
ふくだ
福田のオッサンもおる｡➡
ねら
ど～いう狙いや？ＪＡＸＡ》
What's JAXA trying to do?
《あ～これはヤバい…｡
お腹減った｡➡
Oh, this is bad.
I'm starving!
Large               Serving
バスで配られたお弁当
少なかったもんなぁ～｡➡
The food they served on the bus wasn't enough...
閉鎖環境って
ちゃんと ご飯あんのかな？➡
They will feed us while we're sealed up here, right?
どうしよう ２週間
お腹鳴りっぱなしだったら…｡➡
What if my stomach growls for two whole weeks...
誰か 次のご飯いつか聞いて～》
Someone should ask when we'll get to eat next.
Ｂ班はこちらです｡
あ お先にどうぞ｡
Team B will go this way.
Please.
(ケンジ)ムッ君！
Mu...
Huh?
ムッ君 ここでお別れだ｡
２週間後に会おう！
Mu, this is goodbye.
I'll see you in two weeks.
おう さらばだ！
Yeah, goodbye.
でたっ…ピッ！
There he goes again.
べっかく
《残れよケンジ お前は別格だ｡➡
You'll make it, Kenji...
You're much more talented than I am.
だんぜん
断然 俺より優れた男だ｡➡
On the survey,
アンケートでも お前の名前➡
Makabe Ke
３位に書いといてやったぞ！
俺の下だけどな｡➡
I ranked you number three.
Makabe Ke
Nanba
After myself, though.
１位はもちろん…》
Naturally, number one was...
着きました｡Ａ班のみなさん｡
We've arrived, Team A.
これが みなさんに入っていただく
閉鎖ボックスＭ－８です｡
This is
where you'll be staying,
sealed box M-8.
オォ～ッ スゲエ！
Wow!
It's like Star Wars.
《スター･ウォーズみて～》
《かっこい～っ！》
It's so cool!
It's like Star Wars.
(福田)スター･ウォーズみたいだ｡
おっちゃん その例え古いわ｡
Huh?
Gramps, that example's ancient.
写真 撮ってもいいですか？
Can we take pictures?
No.
ダメです｡目に焼きつけて下さい｡
Try to remember as much as you can.
Now,
それじゃ皆さん 私どもで用意した
作業着に着替えて下さい｡➡
please change into your work clothes.
こういしつ
更衣室はあちらです｡
The dressing room is over there.
《えっ ふ 服？持ってきたのに｡
重かったのに…》
E-Er, clothes?
I brought clothes...
And they were heavy.
ヘッヘ ヒハホヒ
オモカッタノニ…｡
(鶴見)以上で説明を終わります｡
That concludes the explanation.
準備は よろしいですね？
Are you ready?
(一同)はい｡
Yes.
(鶴見)では…➡
In that case...
いってらっしゃい｡
Godspeed.
よし！
ちょ～待てや 南波っ！
Okay.
Hold on, Nanba!
(古谷)ジブン ちゃうやろ
一番に入んのは！➡
You shouldn't be the first one in.
何が よしやねん！こ～ゆ～のは
背の順って決まってんのじゃ！
That's not cool.
Shortest goes first.
That makes me next.
じゃあ 次は私だな｡
失礼しま～す｡
Excuse me...
ど～ぞ お兄さん｡
Go ahead,
big brother.
なんや 中はフツーやな｡
Oh, it's pretty normal inside.
Team B
昔 ＪＡＸＡの一般公開の時に見た
閉鎖施設とそっくりだよ｡
It looks just like the facility I saw during a JAXA tour.
きたむら
へえ～そうなんだ｡私 初めて｡
Oh, really? This is my first time.
みぞぐち
(溝口)みんな見てよ｡
閉鎖施設なのに窓があるよ｡
Look, everyone...
This sealed environment has windows.
もりしま
(森嶋)窓があるな｡
しみず
(清水)なるほど｡➡
Team C
There are windows.
I get it.
今 宇宙にいるんだ 私達｡
So we're in space.
What? Lame.
(古谷)何やこれ しょぼ！
窓っぽく見せてるけど➡
It looks like a window, but it's just a poster of space.
壁に宇宙のポスター
貼ってあるだけやん！
君は アレだね｡
思ったこと全部言うね｡
You aren't afraid to speak your mind, huh?
I shoot straight.
正直者やねん｡
お～い 古谷君｡
Hey, Furuya.
自由な発言は結構だけど➡
Huh?
You can say whatever you want,
ここが宇宙船なら
試験官達は管制室にいる｡➡
but if this is a spaceship,
then the judges are Mission Control.
全部 管制に筒抜けだよ｡
いいのか？
They can hear everything you say.
Are you okay with that?
フフン｡
心配ないって 新田君｡
Don't worry about me, Nitta.
Huh?
俺の物言いが
減点対象になるんやったら➡
If they had a problem with my complaints, I wouldn't be here right now.
今頃 俺ここにおらへん｡
ＪＡＸＡさんは 器がデカイ！
JAXA is very forgiving.
かんよう
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]寛容な人達や！
They're generous people!
寛容だってさ 俺達｡
りじちょう
聞こえました？理事長｡
He thinks we're generous.
Director, did you hear that?
なすだ
(茄子田)あ～ん 彼うまいよね｡➡
That was smooth... He just gave them some leeway.
今ので発言のラインを上げたよ｡➡
これでね ある程度
づか
強い言葉遣いもできると｡➡
Now they won't be afraid to say anything critical.
Ａ班は他の班より
思い切った話し合いができるね｡
We'll get to hear Team A really speak their minds.
理事長 Ａ Ｂ Ｃ班 全員ﾎﾞｯｸｽ内に
入りました｡準備ＯＫです｡
Director, Teams A, B, and C have entered their boxes.
Everything is ready.
よ～し じゃあ 始めちゃおう！
Okay, then let's get started.
お腹痛いの？
Hmm? What's wrong, Se—
Itou?
Does your stomach hurt?
No, I'm fine...
いえ 大丈夫です｡
《減ってるだけです》
I'm just hungry!
You look a little pale.
でも 顔色悪いし…｡
あ いえ｡
No, it's okay.
オッホン｡え～ オッホン｡➡
皆さ～ん ようこそ｡
うわさの茄子田です｡➡
Welcome, everyone. This is Nasuda.
むか～し 一般の大学生を
やと
バイトで雇って➡
We once paid a college student
to stay inside a sealed box for ten days.
同じような閉鎖ボックスに
１０日間 入ってもらいました｡➡
It was an experiment to determine the psychological effects.
精神に どういう影響があるかを
見るための実験でした｡➡
そしたら あの～
８日目くらいだったかな…｡➡
And around the eighth day, I think it was...
あれ？だよね？ねっ｡
彼はちょっと その～➡
Uh, is that right? Yeah?
He started to lose his grip,
テンションが
おかしくなってしまい➡
カメラに向かって
お尻ペンペンを繰り出しました｡
and began mooning the camera.
そ～いうことが起こりうるのです｡
It's entirely possible,
陽の当たらない
閉鎖空間というのはね｡
when you're trapped in a closed space without sunlight.
さあさあ プチ情報は以上にして➡
Okay, that's enough talk.
１つ目の課題は
あたくしから出題します｡➡
I'll now give you your first assignment.
え～ 課題１はクイズで～す｡➡
Task number one is a quiz.
There should be a box on the table...
テーブルの上に
箱がありますよね｡➡
で 中に止まった時計と
電池があります｡
The box contains a stopped clock and a battery.
さて 今 何時でしょう？➡
So, what time is it right now?
５人で話し合い
時計を合わせて下さい｡➡
Please discuss amongst yourselves before answering.
You have ten minutes.
制限時間は１０分～｡
《そんなの朝ごはんの時間よ！》
What time is it? It's time for breakfast!
《何やその問題 小学生か！》
Is this some quiz for grade schoolers?
《何時か…》
What time is it?
《制限時間１０分》
Ten minutes to solve...
Don't be so quiet, everyone.
《お願いみんな｡
そんなシーンとしないで！➡
今もし お腹鳴ったら…》
If my stomach growls...
う～ん どうしましょうかね～！
What do we do...
《聴こえた？
聴こえてないよね？ＯＫ！》
Did they hear?
Looks like they didn't...
Okay!
とりあえず
それぞれで計算してみて➡
A-Anyway,
how about if we each make a guess, and then compare?
答えを出し合うっていうのは
どうですか？
Right.
そうだね｡
そうしよう｡
《ホッ》
Let's do that.
Whew...
Fukuda Yasushi
Icebreaker ends at 5:00 PM.
Another 150-170 minutes pass.
7:30-9:00
10:00-5:00 AM
6:00 AM
Itou Serika
Departure
10 minutes x 14 people - 140 minutes
+10 minutes + 20 minutes - 170 minutes
Meal 8:00 PM-10 PM
Lights off 11 PM-5:30 AM
+ 1 hour
6:30
Nitta
Departure at 3:30 - Icebreaker at 4:30
140 minutes plus change - 180 minutes
(around 3 hours)
7:30 meal-9:00
Lights off 10:00
Wake-up 5:00 + 40 minutes
5:40
Nanba Mutta
Three AM
(古谷)南波兄だけ ＡＭ３時｡➡
Only Nanba's big brother has 3 AM.
他のみんなは 朝５時から６時半｡
Everyone else says it's between 5 AM and 6:30 AM.
So a majority says that it's morning.
多数決で朝に決まりやな｡
中間とって答えは６時にしとこか｡
We'll go with 6:00, since that's in between.
南波君は なぜ３時だと思うのか
聞きたいな｡
I'd like to know why Nanba thinks it's 3:00 AM.
えっ？いや…｡
Huh? Well...
He probably just used a random number.
ど～せ適当やろ｡
ほら これ見たら分かるやん｡➡
Look at his paper!
み～んな それなりに
計算してんのに➡
Everyone else jotted down calculations, but he just wrote an answer.
南波だけ３時 ポーンって！
Nanba Mutta
Three AM
やる気ゼロやん｡
He isn't even trying.
《もし３時だったら
朝までもたない…》
If it really is 3 AM, I won't last until breakfast.
これ見てると お兄ちゃん以外は
みんな同じような計算だな｡
It seems everyone else used the same calculation.
⦅あ スタート！⦆
Start!
バスが出てから
約１時間後に例の交流会｡➡
The icebreaker began about an hour after the bus departed.
10 minutes times 15 people is 150 minutes.
１人１０分間を１５回で１５０分｡
間の ロスタイムを入れて
この時点で出発から➡
Factor in the breaks,
and that puts us around 4 hours...
４時間近く経ってる
計算になるよな｡それから…｡
And then...
ちょっと待って｡
Hold on.
そんな計算
いらないんだよね｡
You really don't need to do all that.
Huh?
The stars I admired were too bright for me
so I quietly closed my eyes
I have faith in you, as you stand alone, full of doubts
I'm right here, next to you
Come now, take my hand and hold it tight
If you do, we will always
have hope, shine with light
and overcome whatever we might face
Do you see how wonderful this world is
and how our future unfolds?
Even the tears we shed and could not put into words
will one day dry up, I am sure
One by one the smiles spread
and ascend towards the starlit sky
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#12 My Name Is Itou Serika
＜閉鎖環境での最初の課題は
今 何時かを当てること＞
Our first task in the sealed environment is to determine the time.
＜フッフ｡
私には勝算があるのです＞
And I know the answer!
That's amazing, Nanba!
＜すごい 南波さん！＞
No, it was just luck, Serika.
＜いや たまたまですよ｡
せりかさん＞
Why are you using Itou's first name?
＜ジブン 何 伊東さんのこと
下の名前で呼んどんねや＞
Huh?
＜えっ？あ～｡ああ ごめん｡
伊東さん｡伊東さん＞
S-Sorry, Itou, Itou!
No, it's okay...
＜ああ いえ…＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
My Name Is Itou Serika.
Nanba, you can use my first name.
＜南波さん｡私のこと 下の名前で
呼んでくれていいですよ＞
パンパカパーン！
今週の➡
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
宇宙写真で～す｡
スッゲエ！
Awesome!